<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Mercurial | Porcupine Programmer]]></title>
  <link href="http://chalup.github.io/blog/categories/mercurial/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://chalup.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-09-26T20:38:06+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://chalup.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Jerzy Chalupski]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Git Killer Feature: Content Tracking]]></title>
    <link href="http://chalup.github.io/blog/2012/04/17/git-killer-feature-content-tracking/"/>
    <updated>2012-04-17T16:20:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://chalup.github.io/blog/2012/04/17/git-killer-feature-content-tracking</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>At my current day job I was the first adopter of git and one of the most frequently question I&rsquo;m asked as &ldquo;the git guy&rdquo; is the variation of &ldquo;why do you use git instead of mercurial?&rdquo;. I usually responded that git was the first distributed VCS I used, and I played for a while with hg and bazaar, but I haven&rsquo;t discovered any significant feature that would make me change my initial choice. Today I have found the case that allows me to give a better answer.</p>

<p>About a month ago I released the <a href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=com.chalup.WordJudgeEN">Word Judge</a> application &ndash; an offline word validator for Scrabble and other word games. Initially I was working only on one version of Word Judge with polish dictionary, so I had one line of code in my git repository:</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/1.png"></p>

<p>When polish version was ready, I decided that I might as well release the english version, because it would require only minor changes: changing app icon and dictionary file. It turned out that I also have to change the application package, so both versions of Word Judge could be installed at the same time. The changes were in fact minor, but included a lot of renaming (package name is mirrored by the directory structure):</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/2.png"></p>

<p>Later on I decided to add ads to my application. First, I&rsquo;ve added the necessary code to master (i.e. polish) branch:</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/3.png"></p>

<p>I switched to english branch, typed <code>git merge master --no-commit</code>, and was very surprised to see just a few conflicts in binary files (icons). All the changes made in java code, <strong>in the renamed files</strong>, were automatically merged. If you still don&rsquo;t get how awesome this is, consider what would I had to do without it:</p>

<ol>
<li>Start the merge</li>
<li>Resolve the conflict by selecting &ldquo;keep deleted files&rdquo; for every java file changed in the master branch</li>
<li>Manually merge every java file from &ldquo;pl&rdquo; package and &ldquo;en&rdquo; package</li>
<li>Delete &ldquo;pl&rdquo; package</li>
<li>Commit changes</li>
</ol>


<p>And I would have to do this <strong>every single time</strong> I port the changes between language branches. It&rsquo;s a tedious and error-prone job, and git automatically (automagically?) does it for me. How cool is that? Mightily cool IMHO. Of course if I add some java files in one branch, I have to do move them to correct package in the other branch (hence the <code>--no-commit</code> switch in git command above), but most of the conflicts are caused by binary files.</p>

<p>It&rsquo;s also more common case than you might think, i.e. you don&rsquo;t have to write a dictionary supporting multiple languages to run into it. For example if you have a lite and full version of an app, you have exactly the same situation.</p>

<p>Right now my repository looks like this (or it would look like this if the git gui tools didn&rsquo;t suck, but that&rsquo;s another story):</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/4.png"></p>

<p>I can&rsquo;t imagine supporting such structure without automatic merges provided by git, because it tracks <strong>content</strong> instead of <strong>files</strong>. And that&rsquo;s the real killer feature that distinguishes git from other DVCS.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
