<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: minSdkVersion | Porcupine Programmer]]></title>
  <link href="http://chalup.github.io/blog/categories/minsdkversion/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://chalup.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-06-20T20:12:45+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://chalup.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Jerzy Chalupski]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[minSdkVersion=15, What's Next?]]></title>
    <link href="http://chalup.github.io/blog/2014/06/15/minsdkversion-equals-15/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-15T09:29:50+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://chalup.github.io/blog/2014/06/15/minsdkversion-equals-15</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A year ago <a href="https://twitter.com/readyState">Jeff Gilfelt</a> was giving away <code>minSdkVersion=14</code> stickers, promoting the idea of dumping the support for Gingerbread and Honeycomb. What seemed radical one year ago, today is a widely accepted. The <code>minSdkVersion</code> in new project wizard in latest Android Studio release is by default set to <code>15</code>. On the same screen you can click the &ldquo;help me choose&rdquo; hyperlink, which shows this screen:</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/android_studio_min_sdk.png"></p>

<p>The percentages are consistent with data from <a href="http://developer.android.com/about/dashboards/index.html">developer.android.com</a> dashboards, but I&rsquo;d say they are skewed towards old Android versions. <a href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=com.futuresimple.base">Base CRM</a> app I&rsquo;m working on has only 3.7% active users on devices with api level &lt; 15 (compared to 17.4% from official Google dashboards). Moreover, if you look only at the new users, the Froyo, GingerBread and Honeycomb is used only by 1%. In this light, supporting pre-API15 devices is a criminal waste, and starting new projects with minSdkVersion lower than 15 a criminal idiocy.</p>

<p>For me, as a delevoper, the <code>minSdkVersion=14</code> is a breakthrough, mostly because of Holo theme available everywhere. I no longer have to worry about <a href="http://localhost:4000/blog/2012/03/08/customizing-ui-controls-on-android/">HTC rounded green buttons and such when creating custom views</a> &ndash; I only have to make them look good with a single theme. Theoretically one could have used <a href="https://github.com/Prototik/HoloEverywhere">HoloEverywhere lib</a>, but it&rsquo;s not a drop-in replacement. First you have to switch to using their Views instead of native ones and adjusting any external UI library to use them as well.</p>

<p>I looked through the <a href="https://developer.android.com/about/index.html">Android changelogs</a> wondering what could be the next version on <code>minSdkVersion</code> stickers. The next step is a small bump to JellyBean (API level 16), which gives us access to actions in system notifications and <code>condensed</code> and <code>light</code> Roboto font variants. Official statictics state that Ice Cream Sandwich is used by 12.3% of users, but this number is much higher than the one from Base statistics &ndash; 5.87%. I expect dropping support for ICS this year.</p>

<p>But then? I don&rsquo;t see anything as groundbreaking as dropping Gingerbread. I don&rsquo;t even see anything with more impact than dropping ICS. Theoretically API level 17 gives access to nested fragments, but I think you should be using support-v4 classes anyways (and if you check the <a href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=com.google.samples.apps.iosched">Google I/O 2014</a> app sources, Google developers seem to think so too). Maybe there&rsquo;s something I missed or something crucial for specific use cases &ndash; do let me know if there&rsquo;s anything in API levels 17-19 you wish you could use already.</p>

<p>Google I/O is coming though, and <a href="https://twitter.com/GabMarioPower/status/477040313832583168">some things indicate</a> we might see Android 5.0 (or at least Android 4.5). Maybe this Android &ldquo;L&rdquo; version will be another breakthrough in development? My personal wish is a new runtime without <a href="https://code.google.com/p/android/issues/detail?id=20814">ridiculous 64k method limit</a>. Of course this opens a lot of other possibilities. Maybe support for Java 8? Or first-class support for other JVM languages? We&rsquo;ll see&hellip;</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Use minSdkVersion=10 for Libraries]]></title>
    <link href="http://chalup.github.io/blog/2014/02/25/use-minsdkversion10-for-libraries/"/>
    <updated>2014-02-25T21:42:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://chalup.github.io/blog/2014/02/25/use-minsdkversion10-for-libraries</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I&rsquo;ve pushed new versions of <a href="https://github.com/chalup/microorm">microorm</a> and <a href="https://github.com/chalup/thneed">thneed</a> to Maven Central today. The most notable change for both libraries is dropping the support for Android 2.2 and earlier versions. The same change was applied to all Android libraries open sourced by <a href="https://github.com/orgs/futuresimple/">Base</a>. Why? <a href="https://plus.google.com/104992412719307414985">+Jeff Gilfelt</a> summed it up nicely:</p>

<blockquote class="twitter-tweet" lang="en"><p>Because it is 2014 <a href="https://t.co/UCMaZOB6Sl">https://t.co/UCMaZOB6Sl</a></p>&mdash; Jeff Gilfelt (@readyState) <a href="https://twitter.com/readyState/statuses/435419373852184576">February 17, 2014</a></blockquote>


<script async src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script>


<p>This tweet is a good laugh (and an excellent example of what happens if you limit the discussion to 140 characters), but there are poor souls who might need an answer they can use as an objective argument. For them, here is my take on this one: you should drop support for Froyo because sizeable chunk of Java 1.6 APIs were missing from API level 8. I&rsquo;m not talking about some dark corners of java packages, I&rsquo;m talking about stuff like <a href="http://developer.android.com/reference/java/lang/String.html#isEmpty%28%29"><code>String.isEmpty()</code></a>, <a href="http://developer.android.com/reference/java/util/Deque.html"><code>Deque</code></a>, <a href="http://developer.android.com/reference/java/util/NavigableSet.html"><code>NavigableSet</code></a>, <a href="http://developer.android.com/reference/java/io/IOException.html"><code>IOException</code></a>&rsquo;s constructors with cause parameter, <a href="http://developer.android.com/sdk/api_diff/9/changes/changes-summary.html">and so on</a>.</p>

<p>Your own code can (and should) be checked with Lint, but these methods and classes can also be used by the 3rd party libraries and I&rsquo;m not aware of any static analysis tool that can help you in this case. So if your app supports Froyo and uses a lot of external dependencies, you&rsquo;re probably sitting on the <a href="/blog/2013/06/26/guava-and-minsdkversion">NoClassDefFoundError bomb</a>. It might force you to use obsolete versions of libraries, the most notable example of which is Guava &ndash; on Froyo you have to use 13.0.1, a 18 months old version.</p>

<p>That&rsquo;s also the reason why the libraries authors should be the first ones to move on to Android 2.3 and later. If you use obsolete library in your application, you&rsquo;re hurting only yourself. If you use it as a library dependency, you&rsquo;re hurting every user of the library.</p>

<p>So move on and bump the minSdkVersion. After all, it&rsquo;s 2014.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[To Guava or Not to Guava?]]></title>
    <link href="http://chalup.github.io/blog/2013/12/27/to-guava-or-not-to-guava/"/>
    <updated>2013-12-27T12:10:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://chalup.github.io/blog/2013/12/27/to-guava-or-not-to-guava</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I faced this dilemma recently, when I was preparing first release of <a href="https://github.com/chalup/cerberus">Cerberus</a> utility for Android. On one hand, in <a href="https://github.com/chalup/cerberus">Cerberus</a> I used a tiny subset of Guava features which can be trivially rewritten in vanilla Java in 15 minutes, so maybe I should not force Guava down peoples throat?  On the other hand I&rsquo;m a <a href="/blog/2013/09/21/guava-goodies">huge</a> <a href="/blog/2013/10/04/more-guava-goodies-abstractiterator">fan</a> of Guava and I think you should definitely use it in anything more complicated than &ldquo;Hello, world!&rdquo; tutorial, because it either reduces a boilerplate or replaces your handrolled utilities with better, faster and more thoroughly tested implementations.</p>

<p>The &ldquo;this library bloats my apk&rdquo; argument is moot, because you can easily set up the ProGuard configuration which only strips the unused code, without doing any expensive optimizations. It&rsquo;s a good idea, because the dex input will be smaller, which speeds up the build and the apk will be smaller, which reduces time required to upload and install the app on the device.</p>

<p>I found the problem though, which is a bit harder to solve. Modern versions of Guava use some <a href="http://developer.android.com/reference/java/util/NavigableSet.html">Java 1.6 APIs, which are available from API level 9</a>, so when you try to use it on Android 2.2 (API level 8), you&rsquo;ll get the <code>NoSuchMethodException</code> or some other unpleasant runtime error (side note: position #233 on my TODO list was a jar analyzer which finds this problem). <a href="/blog/2013/06/26/guava-and-minsdkversion">On Android 2.2 you&rsquo;re stuck with Guava 13.0.1.</a></p>

<p>This extends also to Guava as a library dependency. If one library supports Android 2.2 and older, it forces old version of Guava as dependency. And if another library depends on more recent version of Guava, you&rsquo;re basically screwed.</p>

<p>One conclusion you can draw from this blog post is that you shouldn&rsquo;t use Guava in your open source libraries to prevent dependency hell, but that&rsquo;s spilling the baby with the bathwater. The problem is not Guava or any other library, the problem are Java 1.6 methods missing from Android API level 8! <a href="http://developer.android.com/about/dashboards/index.html">The statistics from Google</a> indicates that Froyo is used by 1.6%, in case of Base CRM user base it&rsquo;s only 0.2%. So more reasonable course of action is finally <strong>bumping minSdkVersion to 10</strong> (<a href="http://dannyroa.com/2013/10/17/why-its-time-to-support-only-android-4-0-and-above/">or even 14</a>), both for your applications and all the libraries.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
